Finding Aid for James A. LeRoy Papers 1893-1944
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James A. LeRoy Papers 1893-1944 1898-1909
LeRoy, James A. (James Alfred), 1875-1909.
2 linear ft.
Writer and diplomat who served in the Philippines, 1900-1901 and 1905, and Mexico, 1903-1907; papers include correspondence, travel journals, photographs, and scrapbooks.
851677 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection came from different sources. In 1943, the estate of Edwin C. Goddard donated the travel accounts of LeRoy's trips to the Philippines. Donor no. 1872 LeRoy's daughter, Mrs. Elizabeth Kallock donated additional miscellaneous materials in the 1970s and 1983. Donor no. 5281
The collection is open for research.
James A. LeRoy was born December 9, 1875 in Pontiac, Michigan. He was educated at the University of Michigan, graduating in 1896. He returned to Pontiac as a public school principal but soon thereafter accepted a position with the Detroit Free Press as a sports writer. He moved on to the Detroit News as a political writer, then to the Baltimore Herald. In 1901, while working in Baltimore, LeRoy came to the attention of Dean C. Worcester, who selected him to serve as private secretary to the Philippine Commission. He easily mastered Spanish and became a student of Spanish and Philippine history. While in the Philippines, LeRoy's work gained the approval of Governor General William Howard Taft who entrusted him with other, increasing responsibilities. Skilled as a writer, LeRoy was uniquely qualified to communicate his impressions of the Philippines in the few years after the 1898 war. In the coming years, he would write extensively, notably his monograph, Philippine life in town and country. Unfortunately poor health forced LeRoy to resign before completing his two-year assignment. He returned to Pontiac and then accepted appointment as consul to Durango, Mexico from August 1903 to March 1907. His service in Mexico was briefly interrupted when selected to accompany now Secretary of War Taft as part of a congressional delegation to the Philippines in 1905. LeRoy died in Fort Bayard, New Mexico on February 26, 1909.
The collection documents the academic career of LeRoy as a student at the University of Michigan and his two trips to the Philippines in 1901 and 1905. The materials have been groups into four series: Biographical/Personal, Philippine Islands, Durango, Mexico, and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Mexico--History--1867-1910.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; LeRoy, James A. (James Alfred), 1875-1909.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Philippines--History--1898-1946.
Contributors:
LeRoy, Mabel.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  The Biographical/Personal series consists of a biographical sketch of LeRoy written by his daughter, correspondence written to his wife while serving in Durango, Mexico, and miscellaneous personal letters.
  - Biographical sketch (Box 1)
  - Letters to his wife
    - 1907 (Box 1)
      (photocopies)
    - January-June 1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1904-1908 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence of Mabel LeRoy, 1909-1944 (Box 1)
- Philippine Islands
  The Philippine Islands series is notable for LeRoy's extended journal account of his activities and observations while traveling in the Philippines in 1900-1901 and 1905. LeRoy was a keen and perceptive observer and his skill as a writer manifests itself in these journal/travelogues.
  - Correspondence, 1900-1902 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence concerning his writings on, and continuing interest in, the Philippine Islands, 1904-1909 (Box 1)
  - Travelogue account of trip to the Philippines, 1900-1901 (Box 1)
    (1987 accession)
  - Manuscript of travelogue account of trip to the Philippine Islands, 1901, 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of travelogue account of trip to the Philippine Islands, 1905, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings relating to the travels of Secretary of War William Howard Taft in the Philippine Islands, 1905, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches of Secretary of War William Howard Taft (Box 1)
  - Philippine miscellanea, 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - Philippine miscellanea, 1905 (Box 1)
  - Article, "Apolenario Mabini on the Failure of the Fililpino Revolution" edited for the American Historical Review, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning publication, contracts, and royalties for book, The Americans in the Philippines, 1913-1927 (Box 1)
  - Photograph album with Philippine Islands views, 1900 (Box 1)
  - "James A. LeRoy's critique of John R. M. Taylor's The Philippine Insurrection against the United States " edited with brief introduction by John M. Gates (Box 1)
- Durango, Mexico
  The Durango, Mexico series consists of a single letterpress book of LeRoy's correspondence while serving in Mexico in 1903-1904.
  - Letterpress book written while serving in Durango, 1903-1904 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series consists of five volumes containing clippings and memorabilia detailing his student life at the University of Michigan in the mid-1890s and his service in the Philippines and Mexico. Included are clipping copies of some of the articles that he wrote for various newspapers.
  - Volume1 1893-1898, (concerns life at the University of Michigan, largely athletic competitions, and copies of articles written for Detroit newspapers) (Box 2)
  - Volume 2, September 1898-September 1899 (Box 2)
    (concerns University of Michigan athletics, and contains copies of sports and political articles written for Detroit newspapers)
  - Volume 3, 1904-1909 (Box 2)
    (contains clippings, largely obituaries of LeRoy, copies of articles, photographs, telegrams)
  - Volume 4, 1900-1918 (Box 2)
    (contains clippings of his newspaper articles, correspondence and memorabilia relating to the life and interests of James A. LeRoy and Mabel LeRoy)
  - Volume 51905, (contains clippings, programs, invitations, and memorabilia from trip to Philippine Islands) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 2)